pay somebody to set up a server with
this on it on Fiverr or freelancer.com,
right? Like even if it's a couple
hundred bucks, like hit up hit up a a
developer that works with this software
stack and just says, "Hey, uh can you
just like put this on the server and set
it up and then you've got it set up.
>> Best part of Viking when you can just,
you know, critical thing, right?
Yeah, dude.
>> All right, hackers. I'm looking at my
inbox right now for hacker 1 and I am
smiling earto ear because I got paid out
a crit and it came from that last CTBB
hackalong that we did live in the
Discord with a couple hundred of you
guys present when I had to cut the
stream and go report a vulnerability
live that resulted in a 7K crit from
Adobe guys. Uh I'm so pleased the Adobe
team also added a $650 bonus to that
report because uh I used the CTBB
partnership code. Okay, so I want to
remind you guys that uh Adobe is
offering a 10% increase in bounties to
you guys, the critical thinking
listeners, because you guys rock. Okay,
and that uh is targeting Adobe Stock and
Lightroom web. Adobe Stock and Lightroom
Web and it is a 10% bonus for valid AI
vulnerabilities mapped to OASP top 10
for LLMs. Okay. Um so definitely go
target those two products, look at the
AI features, and report some awesome
bugs and you'll get that 10% bonus.
We'll put the the uh information down in
the description. The code is CTB063026.
That's June 30th, 2026 because that's
when the promotion ends. Okay, go tear
them up, guys. They're a really good
program. They're paying some great
bounties and they're offering some
special love to you guys, the CTB
listeners. All right, let's go back to
the show. All right, sup hackers. Before
we hop into the episode today, uh we've
got the this weekend bug bounty segment.
Just took some rapid fire news for you.
The only item on our list actually is
very relevant to the episode and it is
the open source security testing guide
uh by Yes, We Hack. Okay. Um so we'll go
ahead and link that down in the
description, but we're going to spend a
lot of time this episode talking about
uh source code review and that sort of
thing. And this while this guide is
focused specifically on open source,
there are a lot of really applicable
techniques here um to any sort of source
code review, right?
um a lot of the tools you need to know,
a lot of the terms you need to
understand. So, give this a glance if
you're getting into that space. Um
there's also another really big added
benefit to these writeups like these
nowadays, which is you can feed these
into your your AI. Hey, say, "Hey, check
this out. Write up a nice little skill
for this based off of this article and
others." Um, one of the ones that I
thought was really nice in this uh,
example was um, mentioning that you can
define uh, bookmarks throughout the
different pieces of code. Uh, that makes
it easier for you to jump around into
different pieces and follow your own
code flows inside of VS Code. Love that.
So, check out this article. It'll be in
the description. All right, let's hop to
the show.
All right, hackers. Today I am
attempting something quite ambitious,
which is I'm going to try to give you
guys um some cross between a meta
analysis and a recipe and just random
thoughts thrown together on source code
review. Um the idea originally for this
episode was like, can I find a way to
grab a bunch of different sources on
source code review, analyze what kind of
patterns we see across all of them, and
kind of put those into one episode. So,
we did that and then I kind of added a
little bit of my thoughts here and
there. We asked a couple experts in the
industry, got their thoughts, pulled all
that in. Um, and that is what this
episode turned into. So, I've spent the
past 3 hours reading through this
document, trying to tweak it, trying to
get it to the spot where it needs to be.
Um, and hopefully a and try to abstract
some of the stuff uh as much as I can.
And hopefully you guys will be able to
get some uh good comprehensive coverage
on the topic of source code analysis.
Okay. Um I think this is a really
applicable topic right now because AI is
is augmenting the space a lot. And while
I will give you some tips on how to use
AI for source code analysis today, most
of this is going to be focused on the
good old here's how you do source code
analysis um source code review. Uh, and
you can then take those and collaborate
with Claude or your AI of choice to to
sort of superpower it. Okay. So, um,
first let's let's go ahead and and jump
right into it. Um, the first thing that
I want to challenge you with if you're
going to do source code review is what
is your goal for this source code
review. Looking at um, a couple of the
main purposes for source code will
reveal a couple things. one for example
if you look at asinode or the SL cyber
team um they are often just looking for
pre-author rce right that's also the
kind of thing you see in pone to own
right if you know that you are just
looking for pre-author rce you know you
have to start from an unauthenticated
route right or you have to bypass
authentication um so that's a you know
if you've defined your goal in advance
hey what I want is unauthenticated RC
then you can start from there if you are
a bug bounty hunter and you're just
looking to cash in maybe you can you
know get bugs uh get rewards for post
off XSS or something like that right um
so it's just it's helpful to know in
your head what am I going for here um
and have that well defined from the
beginning okay so next I kind of wanted
to throw a little theory out there
before we jump into everything I've been
sitting here looking at all the
vulnerabilities that sort of powered
this episode and um all the articles and
stuff like that and And I think I think
that there are really three areas that
almost all of the vulnerabilities that
we find sort of sort of uh come together
sort of narrow down to when you think
about it. The first one is tracing the
data flow better than the developer. The
second one is knowing the nuances of the
context where your payload is landing
better than the developer. And then the
third and last one is just of course the
developer makes some sort of mistake and
forgets a security control. So let's
look at each one of those really quick
and kind of talk about those from a high
level so that we can understand where
all the other vulnerabilities that that
um you'll see sort of how it falls into
that model and you can start thinking
about it from a more abstracted
perspective. Okay. So tracing the data
flow better. Um, this often, you know,
this is a pretty common scenario where
the developer just doesn't understand
that what they are working with at the
time is user input. Um, I'm going to
give you an example of this from a real
vulnerability that I found. Um, we, me
and my buddy, we uploaded a zip file and
this uh, it extracts and pulls a file
out of that zip and then inside of that
file there's XML and inside of that XML
there's an attribute. Okay? And
somewhere down in the pipeline that
attribute got embedded into a command
line shell out and we were able to
escape that that command line argument
and get RC via command line injection.
Okay. And that's a classic scenario of
like oh because it was so abstracted
because you know they had parsed the XML
the XML was different from the file it
was you know far away from the zip you
know it was it was in a job that was not
even you know correlated with that
original HTTP request. I think the
developer just didn't realize that they
were dealing with malicious input here.
Okay. So this is one of the things that
we're going to talk about a good bit in
this in this um session uh is you just
really need to get super good at tracing
data flow. Like I know that that is
super dumb and basic to say, okay, but
really that's the meat of it is you need
to know if data is coming in, right?
Where where is it going all the way
through the pipeline, right? If there's
one skill that I can tell you to master,
it's that just tracing where the data is
going to go through all of the sources
all the way to the syncs. Okay. Um,
second one is knowing the nuances of
where your payload is landing better
than the developers. Um, there's a
really good example of this. Let me go
ahead and pull it up here in um, one of
the SL cyber writeups. I'm going to
reference them a lot. Um, shout out to
Shubs and the team for also helping with
this episode. Um, I'm going to I'm going
to share my screen here as well so that
you guys can see this this snippet uh,
from the um, from the write up. But
essentially it says another key
implementation here uh
implementation detail that must be well
known by those writing any file and path
operations in C is how path combine
works. We've seen this throughout our
careers as source code auditors where
the usage of path combine leads to
critical vulnerabilities. If the second
argument of path combined, usually the
user input, if it is an absolute path,
the previous argument is completely
ignored and the absolute path is
returned. The documentation does try to
make this obvious be this behavior
obviously stating and then proceeds to
quote the documentation which says the
exact same thing. Okay. Um, so this is a
perfect example of like, hey, the
developer thinks that what they're doing
with path combine is prepending, you
know, a uh, you know, a certain path
that locks the user into a directory,
but really you can supply an arbitrary
directory and as the second argument and
it just removes the first argument,
right? Um, and so that's a classic
example of like, well, if you understand
the nuances of this technology better
than the developers themselves, um, then
you'll be able to find vulnerabilities
like path traversal or I guess it's not
really even a traversal here, it's just
arbitrary path injection here. Um,
another classic example of this like
understanding the nuances of the the
payload or the the context in which your
your um, input is getting injected is
xxe, right? A lot of people don't
realize when they're parsing XXE or par
parsing XXE. Man, you can see in my
hacker brain when they're when they're
parsing XML that XML has this crazy
ability to like request files and like
send HTTP requests and stuff like that.
Like why would why would it have that?
Um and the only way that you can exploit
that is by knowing more about XML than
the people using the XML, right? Um, so
number two here on the list is knowing
the nuances of where your payload is
landing better than developers. And this
takes a lot of work and AI can certainly
help with this, right? You can you can
ask it to learn about a specific
technology stack or um even a specific
function, how it's implemented. Uh,
right, we saw that with with path
um the path combine call out there. Um,
yeah, just really need to know where
your p where your your input is landing
in what context. And we'll talk a little
bit more later about the more complex
that context, the better. Okay. And then
last but not least on my list of three
items is forgetting a security control.
Okay. Um, this one's basic. There are
security controls in place in the app.
Uh, or maybe there aren't any at all and
they just completely forgot about
security altogether. But if somebody
forgets a security control, then of
course you can just boop plop in there
and exploit it. Okay. So here are the
main things abstracted up as high as I
can uh that you should look for. Tracing
the data better than than the the
developers themselves. Realizing that
you control a piece of data deep deep
deep in the app. Um knowing the nuances
of where your payload lands better than
the developer, right? understanding the
context and then looking for forgotten
security controls or l you know the lack
of security controls in general. Okay,
so those are some sort of abstracted
stuff that I thought you guys might
benefit from. Um I keep that under the
set your goal um heading uh because
these are sort of things we need to
think about as we're going into the app.
Okay, now let's talk about getting our
hands on the software. Um a lot of times
we have open source software and that's
great. we can just audit the source code
directly from there. And you may even
want to pick your target based off of
the fact that you have access to source
code. Uh I've talked on an episode
recently about hacking on SDKs. Those
are really good uh attack surface
because you have the source code for the
SDK and you can just audit it and look
for vulnerabilities in there. Um but if
you need to get your hands on uh source
code and it's not open source, there are
a couple ways you can do it. One, you
got to look for Docker images supplied
by the organization. that's a great way
to do it. Um AWS, Azure or GCP images
also in the cloud environment. Sometimes
they have um those set up so that you
can uh set up that software and get a
trial or whatever um moving very quickly
without having to talk to a sales team.
We've seen that a couple times. Um I
figure I'll just shout this out as well.
You also should look into packages and
related packages um to the actual main,
you know, app uh in pip and npm. uh we
just saw recently with cloud code, you
know, cloud code, we can look at the
minified JavaScript or whatever, but
they shipped their map files, right? And
uh you know, if if you've got the map
files, that makes your life a lot
easier. Um so make sure you check uh the
repositories
um the packages, the package managers.
That's what I'm saying. Uh the package
manage repos and know that those are not
necessarily going to correlate with a
GitHub repo. you know, there may not
even be a GitHub repo, but even if there
is a GitHub repo, note that there may be
something different in the the package
manager um there. So, keep that in mind.
Um another option is reversing it,
right? Uh we oftentimes will get a
binary or something like that and it's
reversible with like peak or uh maybe if
you got a jar, you can convert it back
to Java or whatever. You got to know
that what type of um language was used
to create this binary and is it possible
for me to reverse stuff out. Um, another
shout lately is that we've been using
Gedra with a very very very dense binary
um and just hooking Claude into it via
MCP.
It's cracked, guys. It's freaking
cracked. And I've actually seen a couple
people on Twitter being like, "Uh, what
the heck? My job is gone." you know,
like like really really good um reverse
engineers just kind of saying sadly like
man this is my art. I've been like
working on this art for a long time and
now Claude can just come in there and
just be like hm it goes like this and
then it goes you know and so um even if
you're not good at reverse engineering
hook claude up to Gedra and you're going
to get some crazy results out of that.
Okay. Um, and then here was another
shout that I, you know, I I I'll have to
look up the source for this where this
came up came from because I didn't see
it in one of the articles. It was
actually from the notes of of our
researcher. Um, but he he noted down pay
somebody to set up a server with this on
it on Fiverr or freelancer.com, right?
Like even if it's a couple hundred
bucks, like hit up hit up a a developer
that works with this software stack and
just says, "Hey, uh, can you just like
put this on the server and set it up?"
and then you've got it set up and that's
the best 200 bucks you've ever spent
spend in your life if you know how much
of a pain it is to get stuff set up. Um
and then you can jump on that that um
server reverse you know grab the code
out and apply some of the other
techniques that we just mentioned. Um
but yeah once you've got your hands on
the code then we go to the next step um
which is you you really do need to set
up the code and get a local environment.
Um, guys, this is where AI is really
super gamechanging, okay? AI knows how
to set stuff up better than anything
I've ever seen in my life, dude. And if
there's one area where I save a lot of
time, it is this. Like, where I just
wouldn't bother with it before cuz it's
like, oh my gosh, this is so
excruciatingly painful to set stuff up.
Like, I just can't do it, right? If
there's not a Docker image, you can just
throw AI at it and AI will turn turn
until it gets it working. Um, such a big
big win to use cloud for this sort of
thing. Um, and then as much as I have
been on the fence about it, hooking a
debugger into this stuff is really
really legendary, guys. Um, I've played
with it a little bit lately and I have
to say like
I I used to be a proponent for just like
try to yeet it at the main server, you
know, look at the source code, try to
figure it out. It's so unbelievably o
overpowered to set a you know a debug
breakpoint and then just be able to see
and inspect live um variables. So if
you're if you're going to sit down and
you're going to be serious about it, if
you're going to reverse some code, get
it spun up, attach debugger and you're
good to go. This is another area where
um AI can really really help a ton.
Okay, so we're we're we're through the
boring stuff here. Figure out a way to
get your hands on the source code and
get that set up and get a debugger
hooked into it. Okay. All right. Next,
mapping the software. Okay. Um, this is
an essential first step. A lot of people
say, "Okay, we we prefer sync based
analysis." If you listen to some of the
episodes back when Joel was a co-host,
we debated a good bit like, "Hey, should
we start at sync? Should we start at
sources? What's the idea here?" Um,
whatever the idea is, you should map the
software first. Okay? And I personally
think that moving from a source
enumeration perspective at the beginning
really gives you a a strong
understanding of the app. Um, but either
way, you need to understand the basic
structure of the app before you you
start going in and trying to find, you
know, the exec function or something
like that where that you want to map up
to a source. Okay. Um, and once again,
AI comes in super clutch here. It can
build you graphs. it can lay, you know,
slurp up the build files, which is one
of the things I wanted to recommend is
taking a look at the actual build files
and um and looking at the various
services that they're sort of, you know,
duct taping together in some of these
enterprise apps. Um, but it can look at
all that stuff and it can create a map
for you of what the application looks
like. And guys, that is so valuable.
Okay. Um, one of the things I've learned
by working really closely with Chubs a
couple times is how
much impact he gets out of finding weird
little APIs that were hidden in a corner
that aren't defined the same way that
have some exception that are routed a
little bit differently and uh, you know,
he turns that into magic time and time
again. Okay, so if you know maybe your
app is just vanilla and it's just normal
you know Python Flask routes in a file
you know but you got to make freaking
sure that that's the case okay and that
there's not any other micros service or
um websocket server or like gRPC
something something you know that's like
hiding in a corner uh that you can go
after. Okay, so that's something you
really have to pay attention to. I noted
I noted just a second ago um that we
should be talking about um you know
these route definitions and the routing.
Well, reverse proxies is another big
piece here. Are they using that reverse
proxy to wall off certain endpoints or
certain parts of the the routing on the
back end, right? Don't just look at the
router and assume that all of that stuff
is accessible and then you know when you
hit your your uh you know production
server you're like, "Oh, that route
isn't accessible." Blah blah blah.
You've got to look at the reverse proxy.
That's the first layer, right? And
understand what they're trying to wall
off. And that also can give you a nice
uh treasure map for what you should get
access to. Okay, reverse proxy
configuration is very important.
Middleware configurations equally as
important. Okay, a lot of times O is
being applied at the middleware level.
So figure out what decorator or um you
know additional piece that gets built
into these routes is applying the O
middleware and check that it is
holistically applied across all the
routes. If it's not, that could be a
good gadget. Okay. Um, so make sure
you're checking all those. You're
looking for websockets. You're looking
for gRPC. You're looking at the reverse
proxies. You're looking at the routes
definitions. And don't skip the boring
parts of all of this. Okay. The Graphana
SSRF that I found in 2020, which is one
that I refer to all the time because
it's such a classic example of uh a a
clean exploit. Okay. Um this exploit was
found in the avatar route for for
graphana. Okay, this is the graphana
ssrf. Um and it would hit gravitar on
the on the on the back end and then uh
got a redirect off of gravitar to AWS
metadata credentials. Okay. And if I had
if I had skipped the avatar route on
graphana, then I would not have found
that. And the avatar route is not
typically the most interesting path,
right? Um, but we really need to be
thorough about it. And it was an
unauthenticated path, which is what drew
me to it in the first place. Um, so make
sure you're being thorough and not
skipping any of those boring boring
quote unquote boring looking paths.
Okay. You know what's going to be boring
is when you don't submit any dang
reports because you didn't look at the
boring routes. Um, so yeah, uh, I
mentioned that you should look for
services that are explicitly not exposed
via the reverse proxy. Um, I also wanted
to mention here that you can use stuff
like assets not asset notes or SL cyers,
excuse me. Uh, hetsu, which is uh, h y o
k tsu. That's Japanese for verdict.
Hetsu. Um, and what that does is it
scans the it supports various um, uh,
source code um, bases. Uh but for
example, it it'll look for jars that are
known uh open source libraries or um
reused code, right? And then you can not
spend your time decompiling all those
and trying to crosscorrelate them. Um so
this is a great way to like get out all
the fluff and look at the meat of what
is the custom code from this
application. Um so then you're not
spending a bunch of time searching for,
you know, zero days in some Apache Jar
file, right? Um, that being said, I also
had in my notes here that sometimes when
the single point of failure might be a
third party library, sometimes it it
it's worth it to to look into that a
little bit. Okay. Um, and it depends on
what program you're working with. You
know, if you're if you're trying to if
they're really not going to pay for
thirdparty bugs, if you're doing this
from a bug bounty perspective, um, you
know, then obviously you need to not do
that on the other hand, right? Um, but I
do often find that if they're using some
rinky dink little like, you know, 200
star on GitHub library, there's a decent
chance that there actually might be a
problem with that. So, that could be
another area where we could see some
tooling get introduced soon is like um
SL cyber hilketsu um sort of I just
wanted to go off in Japanese there. uh
like the Hilketssu something that looks
like Hilketssu uh but for identifying
open source libraries or um you know
reused code that is very low star on
GitHub or on the package managers or
whatever right um that could be another
really interesting attack surface to go
after if they're using a a a not very
popular dependency
um just a thought um once again just
sort of jumping into the AI for this
specific section. Um, really this we you
really want to be using AI for mapping
this out. This is one of the biggest
productivity gains you gain with AI
right now is I feel like I can ingest a
codebase in like freaking 30 minutes
now. Whereas it would take four, five,
six hours sometimes before to like
understand, okay, this is here, this is
there, you know, and I feel like I have
a good good grasp of it 30 minutes in.
Um, very very helpful. massive
productivity gains. Okay, so we've
covered um you know, set your goal, set
up the software, um get your hands on
the software, that sort of thing. Um map
the software, and now we're going to go
into now we we understand the
architecture, we understand the attack
surface, and we're going to start doing
the actual assessment. Okay. Um, I I
always kind of call this segment
um this portion sniffing for blood
because there are just so many,
how do I put this? There are so many
signs. There are so many like um
patterns that will just give you a
sketchy feeling if you've done this for
a little while. And even if you haven't
done this for a little while, if you've
read a lot of writeups, you'll look at
something and you'll be like, "That's a
little weird." Right? Um, and I was
trying to figure out how to abstract
that up. And the only way that I think I
can describe it is when our user input
and like enters a more complex
environment. Okay, that's I think that's
really the root of it is our our you
know if our string input that comes from
a query parameter or something like that
is just compared to a string, right? You
know, it's not that complex. There's not
a lot of wiggle room there, right? it's
not probably setting off your alarm
sensors for like um you know this could
be vulnerable.
If instead our query parameter is put
into a configuration file that con
controls you know has a whole language
in this configuration file that's at our
disposal then you know the gears start
turning a little bit here where you're
like wow my simple user input just ended
up in a really complex environment. Same
thing we see with XSS, right? You know,
when we one of the ones I love to point
to is if our input is inputed inside of
a string, inside of a script tag, inside
of HTML, right? There are just so many
layers of complexity there, right? How
is that string used? We've got string um
features we can use with like backslash
unicode escapes. We've got um he
hexodimal definitions. Uh you've got so
many different things. And then you've
got the script layer. Okay, now we're in
JavaScript. You know, what can I do
here? Let me break out with a single
quote. Um, okay, we're in HTML. I I got
to make sure that those, you know, angle
brackets and the slash are are escaped
even if the single and double quotes are
because I can just cut off the tag,
right? There's just so many layers of
complexity um when our user input ends
up in various context. And as that
complexity continues to increase, that's
where things get sketchy. Okay, so
that's the one of the more high high
level principles that I would like to
convey to you is look for your input
entering complex environments. What are
some complex environments? Well, let's
talk through some of those. Okay, I
created a little list here. Um, of
course, we have the traditional ones
like um database strings, right? Like
SQL injection. Um, why is that complex?
There's various encodings we can use.
there's there's um you know inside of
the SQL or database string right there
is uh a syntax there double quotes
single quotes or strings you know that
sort of thing that's an increasing
complexity and comes along with massive
capability right if it gets if it just
gets complex that's great but we also
have to be able to do something right if
we can break out of our string in a
database we can query the database write
to the database sometimes execute
commands Okay, complexity plus
capability very important. Some other
areas where we might see that
complexity. I mentioned config files
from before. I think configuration file
injection is a super underrated
vulnerability type. There's different
language syntax, there's encodings,
there's there's uh you know some of
these languages you can just like
JavaScript or um you know inside of the
JavaScript screen you can write in
escaped hex, right? Um there's all sorts
of stuff. Unicode, right? So definitely
configuration file injection. Um if our
user input ends up in a URL, we've got
traversals. We've got the various parts
of the URL that we can um create
segments for. Question mark pops us into
the query. Uh hashtag pops us into the
hash, right? If we're defining the the
domain portion, the at sign pops us into
the username and password field. Right?
The there these areas where there are
different grammars in place. that's
where we need to be, you know, living.
And it takes an understanding of the
technology that you're working with,
right? Which is why that mapping and
understanding the architecture of the
application and the technology base that
you're working with is super important.
And answering some of those core
questions like, okay, my input just
ended up here. What capabilities does
that have? Okay. And that brings it all
back up to the top when I was talking to
you guys in the beginning about
understanding the nuances of where your
payload lands better than the developer
who wrote it, right? That's what we're
talking about here with this complexity.
Okay, so hopefully I didn't drive that
home too hard. Uh here are a couple
other ones that are interesting. Um if
your input lands in an API request body,
not just the path, right? That's also
interesting. Can you um escape out of
the JSON? Freaking Fron Rosen told me to
start doing this. I was like, dude,
nobody ever like doesn't use a library
to parse JSON or create JSON. And then I
started looking for it and I found a
couple of them and I was like ate my
words there. So, um, make sure you're
looking for weird concatenation of of
JSON, um, XML, other entities, you know,
even some of these binary protocols. I
just talked last week about, um,
Protobuff structures, right? Binary
Protobuff structures, um, being able to
input into these very impactful
sometimes. Um, we're looking at
templates, concatenation with templates.
Um, and one of the ones that Shubs
called out as well as an increasingly
complex environment is any sort of
dynamic code evaluation paths. This is
something that I've seen uh shubs do
really well. Um, he me mentioned a
couple XSLT, Rhinocript, uh, Jel, um,
any sort of sandbox environment where
you are getting, you know, plopped into
a sandbox. Uh, those are really
interesting to look at. So your your
alarm should be going off boom boom boom
boom whenever you see our input landing
in dynamic code evaluation paths or
increasingly complex environments. Okay,
hope I drove that home. Um, another
thing to look for that kind of uh leads
to that that weird tingly spidey sense
on where the vulnerability is is code
that seems to be implemented in a
different way or le you know a legacy
way from the main codebase. So once
you've mapped out the architecture um
you know you understand what where is
the majority of the functionality
living? It's living in this main API
that's defined in this flask blahy blah.
Um but as soon like even if there's
another API completely whichever one's
not the like main API is just inherently
interesting. So um that's another area
to look for for um for issues. Okay. I
tried to I I tried to get as much of
that abstracted as possible. Um and I I
think there are probably a lot of other
areas where where you can um sniff for
blood, right? where you can sort of um
where you get a spidey sense for where
the vulnerabilities may be. But these
are the ones that I came up with that I
thought were most abstractable. Um okay,
now let's talk a little bit about uh
some common pitfalls and then we'll go
into some patterns that sort of extend
actually you know what let's jump over
to the patterns first. We'll we'll jump
to the patterns and then we'll jump back
to the actual things that seal the deal
in some of these environments. Okay. So
what kind of patterns do we see in
addition to um our our input landing in
increasingly complex environments which
often results in vulnerabilities. And we
pulled these from a bunch of different
research, a lot of the asenote writeups,
um a lot of just stuff I have bookmarked
on on Twitter, um a lot of talks across
YouTube on um source code analysis, that
sort of thing. And we kind of put them
into like top five bullet points here um
to try to show you guys what what we've
got. So the first one that came up is
parser differentials. Um this is
something that uh the team over at Yes
WeHack uh has done an excellent job of
writing up recently. So definitely check
that out. We'll link that in the
description. But um there are going to
be a lot of uh a lot of scenarios where
parser differentials um cause
vulnerabilities. And one of the most
common patterns I've seen here is there
being a well- definfined security layer
and then there being a well- definfined,
you know, application layer. and the
security layer. I've noticed that if the
security layer just gives you a yes no
then it's it's less effective and that
isn't always the case right but one of
the things I really like to do is you
know look at the security layer and and
the security layer doesn't pass the
input to the application layer is what
I'm trying to say so example request
comes in hits the security layer the
security layer says okay and then it
passes the request to the application
layer right um versus the security layer
saying uh here's the information to the
application layer. Does does that make a
little sense? There's like a direct
handoff between the the security layer
and the application layer. And the
reason for that is um there are two
preparation processes is is what I'm I'm
calling it right now. I'm sure there's a
different way to um define it, but
whenever you're parsing unstructured
data, um for example, we'll just give
the example of a JSON parse, right?
Let's say your your security layer lives
in in a JavaScript environment and using
JSON.parse
and I'm just pulling this out of my out
of my hat here. Um and and your backend
is using Python which uses JSON.loads,
right? These are two different parsing
environments and there might be a
differential between those two. And so
the security layer can just say sure
here you know this seems fine pass it
you know pass it back and say all good
and then the routing layer you know sort
of passes it to the application layer on
the back end versus let's say a scenario
where you have something more monolithic
um a JavaScript security layer and and a
JavaScript um backend and it just passes
the object directly from the security
layer into the um the application layer.
Okay, does that make sense? So there's
there's there's different preparation
processes across the front end and the
back end where the security is
implemented in the front. I hope that
makes sense. There's lots of different
examples of parser differentials um
across lots of different uh
environments. So just be on the lookout
for those on how the data is being
processed. Um next was uh chaining.
Okay, that's another common um scenario
that we see is that a lot of times these
more complex vulnerabilities especially
in the enterprise applications are not
single bugs. They are multiplechained
bugs together and this is where I start
to think AI is going to have some
problems. Certainly we should be using
AI and really AI is great for this,
right? Uh we can tell it, hey, look,
I've got this. I've got this. I've got
this. actually just told it like an hour
ago. Look, I've got this CSPT. I need an
arbitrary JSON hosting primitive. Okay,
find me this find it for me now, you
know, and and it, you know, goes across
everything it knows across about the
codebase and it says, look, the most
likely places for this to exist are
here, here, here, and I'm going to work
through them one by one. And it goes
through it and you go through it at the
same time and you're, you know, handing
stuff back and forth, right? So I would
really encourage you guys as you use AI,
you know, one of the things it's not
great at is yet is doing this
multiplechain thing, right? So you have
to be the multiple chain thing. Make it
document gadgets, make it document
things that you you know that you've
used in other pieces of in other chains,
right? This is the importance of like
maintaining a nice claude MD file that
where the the AI knows, okay, arbitrary
JSON hosting for Justin is a very very
valuable gadget, right?
um and then bringing them together uh to
complete the chains and and same for um
same for just forcing it to find the
other piece of the chain that you need,
right? Then you don't have to go through
uh the all the mental duress of like,
man, I really need an open redirect
right now. Like where the heck am I
supposed to find an open redirect? And
you kind of offload it to the AI, see
what it comes out with. Okay, so good
stuff there. chaining is essential to
high quality um uh you know source code
auditing in my opinion. Okay, next up is
dependency auditing. I sort of mentioned
to the this to y'all before, but if
you've got a dependency that looks a
little sus, it might be a good idea to
take a peek at that, especially if it's
low stars or um the source code just
looks a little different, right? Um, I
h, this one was one I added in myself
because I've been finding
vulnerabilities here. Um, and typically
when they're in programs that value
impact, they pay pretty dang well. Um,
so don't sleep on that. And I wish, you
know, I I hope all the guys like Ronnie
and and uh the people that do dependency
confusion vulnerabilities, uh I hope
they that that becomes a little bit more
widely accepted in the bounty space
right now because um man, it is it is
impactful. Uh if you compromise a
dependency and then boom, your whole
source code's gone. Really crazy. Um
okay. Uh, next one is the validate then
transform
um code pattern. We see this pretty
often. You know, there's something for
me the episode I mean I was pretty far
into my, you know, professional hacking
career when I did this the DOM purify
episode with Kevin Misu. But in that
episode for me is where it became super
concrete. What Kevin was emp emphasizing
in that episode was that if you do
anything anything to the string after
you put it through DOM purify then it is
polluted and you can very very very
likely you know cause a problem. The the
DOM purify sanitization step needs to be
like pretty much wrapped in the whatever
is going to write write it to the DOM um
for this to actually work properly. Um
and similarly any sort of sanitization,
any sort of uh validation checking um
that you do for vulnerabilities really
needs to be right before the sync where
it is where it would potentially be
abused. Okay, I'm going to say that
again. When there is some sanitization
or or um checks for malicious input, it
needs to be right before the place where
it would be maliciously used. Okay, if
it's not any anything in that space is
interesting, right? what happens between
the check and the actual sync. Um that
is a one of the most common things that
we see is you know code gets more
complex over time that that little
segment between the validation and the
sync gets bigger when somebody adds in a
little feature here or there, right? Um
so make sure you're checking that space
between the validation and the sync. Um
another big one that I've seen often is
alternative sources. Okay, I'm going to
tell you guys a quick story about this
one. So, I was banging my head up
against an app. I was like, man, if I
could get XSS here, this would be
gamechanging because of the way of the
the way the app works, right?
Unauthenticated input, it would be
great. Um, anyway, it would compromise
the whole app because of wormability.
Okay, so I was banging my head up
against this markdown uh editor and I'm
like, surely there's something here I
can find. Couldn't find it. Anyway, I
notice that there's also a way for me to
send text messages into this
application. And I'm like, "All right,
you know, let me let me let me try that
out." So, I whip out my phone. I write
a, you know, message uh an actual uh
HTML message on my phone and I send it
and I typed it. So, I send it again and
it pops on the admin panel and I'm like,
freak yes. Um so one of the takeaway
from this being is look for al alternate
sources into the place where you want
your data to to live. Okay. Um surely
there's going to be the traditional path
but there's also going to be maybe
legacy endpoints v1 v2 v0ero endpoints
right there's going to be alternate data
streams. Is data coming in from SMS? Is
data coming in from websockets? Is data
coming in from you know being loaded in
via a mass import from a configuration
file? Right? Maybe that one's missing
the san sanitization that's happening at
the source rather than the sink. And
that's why we we sanitize more at the
sink rather than at the source because
like there's, you know, you have to hit
every single source, right? Versus if
you sanitize right before the sync, then
you know, you know, it's just going to
go right into the sync. Does that make
sense? Okay. I I hope it does. So look
for alternative sources for data to flow
into the application and look for
patterns of where they're putting that
sanitization. if they're putting it at
the source or at the sync. Um, yeah, and
and I just wanted to say, you know, in
with regards to AI and these common
patterns, you can take these patterns,
we'll we'll have them in the hacker
notes, and you can tell AI, hey, look
for these across the application. Look
for sanitization that is far from the
the sync. Look for um, you know, SUS
dependencies. look for this um you know
alternative sources into the same spot.
Look for the look for these gadgets that
I need. Um AI is just here to bolster
all of that uh as you as you do your
security assessment. Okay. Um now let's
jump into a couple common pitfalls that
sort of close the deal in a lot of
situations.
I I ranted a little bit about this on a
recent episode, but freaking casing,
guys. Let me tell you, casing causes a
lot of dang problems, okay? So, just
keep that in mind. Um, uppercase letter,
lowercase letter, things are going to
parse those things, you know, the same
or different, right? Um, and it's good
to know which one's which. Unicode
normalization much like uh you know the
casing is also something that is uh
often causes a lot of problems. That
one's a little bit less easy to spot in
the source code review. Um that is
something that you could shout to AI and
be like yo you see any like unic code
normalization issues here uh where you
know Unicode is potentially being
processed. Um could be a a good a good
piece. Once again, you'll see that more
in increasingly complex environments. If
you're handing off from one technology
stack to another technology stack, what
are the assumptions that are between
these two technology stacks? Okay, that
may not hold true in all edge cases.
Um, another one that's really funny that
we see really often too, I'll give you
non- global replacement and bad reax.
Like they get their own shout outs here
because they are so common. Okay, if
somebody's trying to replace something,
they very very often forget the uh you
know the global piece or the recursive
element of it, right? You know,
especially when they're sanitizing with
a replace that's just hect. Okay, so
anytime you see a replacement on your
input, just like stare at it for a
couple minutes and be like, hm
h
and something will jump out to you.
That's what I do. I just I say replace.
All right, I'm going to be staring at
this for the next 10 15 seconds at
least. Um definitely a good use of time.
Um bad reax like I mentioned a second
ago very common dot escapes missing um
you know up arrow at the beginning or
dollar sign at the end super common. Um
look look deep into this uh because
there are there are really some some
things that people can miss here. Um one
of the ones that I really like is a
backslash inside of square brackets.
trying to escape stuff that you don't
need to escape and accidentally putting
the backslash character inside of square
brackets and thinking that it's it's uh
you know it's actually backslash
escaping something. Okay. Um really
really fun scenario there. Uh encodings
another thing you know we mentioned uh
unicode but you've you got to master all
of your encodings of course. Um
yeah incomplete syntax checks is another
really big one. For example, I mean the
big one that just comes to your mind is
like, oh, if they're just looking for
like script tag for XSS input. These are
this I'm giving you this example. I know
you know this, right? But let's
generalize it a little bit. Let's
abstract it a little bit to any sort of
incomplete syntax checks. Anytime you
are looking for, you know, the the code
is looking for a specific syntax to
disallow, right? That's when we need to
think, okay, is that disallow list, is
that block list really thorough or not?
And are there any cases? Can I
capitalize my script tag? Can I, you
know, use a SVG on event handler? Right?
Um, what else can I do here that will um
address this incomplete block list? Very
common. These are the kind of things
that seal the deal, right? Once you
found you smi sniff the blood, you find
an unauthenticated route from the legacy
API, you go in there, you're looking at
the code, bad sanitization, boom, xss,
boom, file read, whatever.
Um, this is one that I added to the list
because we see it a lot with like rce
writeups, which is, you know, something
that we used largely for this um, uh,
meta analysis here, uh, is dynamic
function calling. So, by this what I
mean, I mean, there's lots of ways that
you can do this, but the one that sort
of rings true for me in PHP, because we
covered it on episode a long time ago
with the um Word Fence team, is this
like really weird method invocation uh
structure where you can just call a
string in PHP, right? You have a string
and it has a functions name in it and
you just call it, right? And it's like,
oh, wow, that works. Like, that's crazy.
Um, so it's really important to do your
your your data tracing there and see if
there's any sort of scenario where
you're essentially doing an RPC, right?
Like a remote procedure call. Um,
because that is is where a lot of yuck
comes in and a lot of flexibility for
the attacker. Okay. Um, so keep an eye
out on an eye for any of those. Keep an
eye out is what I meant to say for any
of those situations. as I'm saying that
keep an eye out is such a weird English
phrase, right? Like keep an eye out like
your eye. Anyway, I I digress. Um, got a
couple more here and then we'll wrap uh
for this episode. Um,
incomplete application like I mentioned
before of security controls. That's
another really big one. Ask the AI. This
is something the AI can really help you
with. Where are the pivotal security
controls here? If they are not globally
applied as middleware,
how how do I check whether everything
has this, you know, function call right
at the beginning of of its route
handler, right? H how do I check whether
um you know there are any weird places
where where this function is not being
called properly or or maybe it's like in
an if statement with another condition
or you know the way that this function
is called seems non-standardized, right?
Like I just mentioned the if if
statement just a second ago. Maybe one
of them is a truthy sort of thing,
right? Um that's another big thing is
truthy issues in in typing checks. Um we
need to be they needs to be consistent
across the board, right? Any sort of off
or um sanitization checks need to be
consistently implemented across the
board and any variance is a very very
common pitfall um and an area that you
should look deeply into.
Um, another one that came up here is
making O decisions off of an
inconsistent source. Okay. Um, like as I
said a moment ago, the middleware if
it's not globally applied, where where
are they getting their off information?
Is this coming from anywhere except this
bearer or this cookie or this one
function that processes it as a part of
the HTTP request? If they are, um, then
we need to know where that is and we
need to double click into that deeply.
Okay. Um, so that's a really big one as
well. Lastly, we have custom sanitizers.
Okay. Um, a lot of times we have things
like Dom purify for a reason, right?
There are going to be um very very
complex environments where our input is
landing. If you see a custom sanitizer,
you need to be very very locked in on
that. And um you may even be able to
instrument it to fuzz it a little bit
better. Um that's something that I've
done in the past. Um, and when you do,
something often falls out. And it may
not be a full bypass, but a partial
bypass sometimes can be enough to give
you another gadget in your chain, which
you can chain with something else.
Um, all right y'all, that's just a bunch
of me ranting about stuff. I We're going
to have a ton of resources linked in the
description uh from this episode that
you can go to learn more about source
code analysis. I tried to summarize it
best I can. I wanted to so really give a
lot of respect to those people um whose
work is in the description. I really
really appreciate the writeups that they
did. But I want to give a special thanks
to Shubs, Rafex, and FSI um for giving
uh direct feedback or direct input into
this episode um and really changing the
way that we that we thought about this
um this episode from the meta analysis
perspective. So, shout out to them. Um
and I hope you guys gain some value out
of that. Keep hacking, y'all. Keep
popping bugs and zero days on these uh
on these code bases. All right. All
right. Peace.
And that's a wrap on this episode of
Critical Thinking. Thanks so much for
watching to the end, y'all. If you want
more critical thinking content, uh or if
you want to support the show, head over
to ctvb.show/isord.
You can hop in the community. There's
lots of great highlevel hacking
discussion happening there on top of
master classes, hackalongs, exclusive
content, and a full-time hunter guild if
you're a full-time hunter. It's a great
time. Trust me. All right, I'll see you
there.